Guide to the Oskar Morgenstern Papers, 1866-1992 and undated RL.10033
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Oskar Morgenstern papers
1866-1992 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Morgenstern, Oskar, 1902-1977
RL.10033
41.8 Linear Feet
Economist, university professor, and author in Austria and U.S., born Carl Friedrich Alfred Oskar Morgenstern in Germany. The papers of Oskar Morgenstern, who is associated with the Austrian School of Economics, span the years 1866-1992, although the bulk of the materials date from 1917 to 1977. They consist of correspondence, diaries, subject files, printed material, audiovisual material, manuscript and printed writings and their supporting papers, and biographical and bibliographical information about his career and publications. The collection principally concerns Morgenstern's work as an economic theorist, university professor, author and lecturer, and consultant to business and government.
27,691 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The papers of Oskar Morgenstern were received as a gift in 1987, 1990, 1991, 1993, 1999, and 2013.
Biographical Note
1902, Jan. 24 Born, Grlitz, Silesia, Germany
1925 Doctorate in political science, University of Vienna
1925-1928 Holder of Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial Fellowship
1928 Published Wirtschaftsprognose
1929-1938 Lecturer and professor in economics, University of Vienna
1934 Published Die Grenzen der Wirtschaftspolitik
1938 Visiting professor in U.S.
1938-1970 Lecturer and professor of economics, Princeton University
1944 Became U.S. citizen Joint author of Theory of Games and Economic Behavior with John von Neumann
1948 Married Dorothy Young
1950 Published On the Accuracy of Economic Observations
1959 Published The Question of National Defense and International Transactions and Business Cycles
1960 Co-founder, Institute for Advanced Studies, Vienna
1962 Co-founder, Mathematica
1963 Published Spieltheorie und Wirtschaftswissenschaft
1970 Published Predictability of Stock Market Prices with C.W.J. Granger Retired from Princeton University
1973 Published Long Term Projections of Power: Political, Economic, and Military Forecasting with Klaus Knorr [and] Klaus P. Heiss
1976 Joint author of Mathematical Theory of Expanding and Contracting Economies with G.L. Thompson
1977 Distinguished Professor in Game Theory and Mathematical Economics, New York University
1977, July 26 Died, Princeton, N.J.
Collection Overview
The papers of Oskar Morgenstern, who is associated with the Austrian school of economics, span the years 1866-1992, although the bulk of the materials date from 1917 to 1977. They consist of correspondence, diaries, subject files, printed material, audiovisual material, manuscript and printed writings and their supporting papers, and biographical and bibliographical information about his career and publications. The collection principally concerns Morgenstern's work as an economic theorist, university professor, author and lecturer, and consultant to business and government.
The first two decades of Morgenstern's career as an economist, the 1920s and 1930s, were associated with the University of Vienna where he was educated and was a faculty member until his emigration to the United States in 1938. He published major books about economic forecasting (1928) and the limits of economics (1934) and numerous other writings in which the subjects of business cycles, prices, the depression of the 1930s, economic conditions in Europe and America, currency and exchange, and economic history and theory are prominent. Information about them is scattered throughout the Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, and Subject Files Series. Morgenstern's interests and correspondents were international, although principally European and American. A considerable part of the correspondence and writings during these years, and all of the diaries, are written in German. English is also prominent, and other languages also occur.
Morgenstern's output of publications during the 1940s, his first decade at Princeton University, was less extensive than in the 1930s, but he and John von Neumann published their classic Theory of Games and Economic Behavior in 1944. As Princeton editor Sanford G. Thatcher wrote in 1987, in sheer intellectual influence, it probably has stimulated more creative thinking, in a wider variety of fields of scholarship, than any other single book Princeton University Press has published. Information about this book and subsequent international developments in game theory pervades the Correspondence, Subject Files, and Writings and Speeches Series until Morgenstern's death. The elaboration of game theory was not only theoretical but also practical, and Morgenstern's writings and projects illustrate its applications, especially in U.S. military and foreign policy during the Cold War.
The Writings and Speeches Series, including the diaries, and the Subject Files Series are extensive for the 1940s as they are for the later decades of Morgenstern's career. The Correspondence Series, however, is extensive only for the 1920s, 1930s, and 1970s. Part of his correspondence apparently did not survive. However, Morgenstern routinely placed letters and other material in his files for subjects and writings, and many letters are to be found there. There are a number of letters for some correspondents, but extensive correspondence with an individual is not characteristic of this collection. A person's letters may be filed in more than one chronological group of correspondence.
Morgenstern published prolifically during the 1950s to 1970s. His major books focused on accuracy in economics (1950), organization (1951), national defense (1958), international finance and business cycles (1959), the peaceful uses of underground nuclear explosions (1967), stock market prices (1970), political, economic, and military forecasting (1973), and expanding and contracting economies in various societies (1976). These books and numerous articles and reviews reveal his interest in economic theory, international economic problems, and the application of mathematics and economics to public policy problems. The Writings and Speeches, Subject Files, and Correspondence Series document many of his publications and such topics as the Cold War, nuclear issues, military and naval affairs (especially the U.S. Navy), defense, space, economic analysis, game theory, the stock market, business cycles, mathematics and economics, statistical validity, and his work with John von Neumann, Martin Shubik, Friedrich A. von Hayek, Gottfried Haberler, Antonio de Viti de Marco, Eveline Burns, Gerald L. Thompson, N. N. Vorob'ev, and others.
Morgenstern taught at Princeton until his retirement in 1970 when be began teaching at New York University, and both schools are represented, particularly in the Subject Files Series. These files and the Writings and Speeches Series document his relationship with public and private organizations, especially the Office of Naval Research, the Rand Corporation, various foundations and scholarly societies, and Mathematica, a consulting firm that did contract work for government and business. Morgenstern was co-founder of Mathematica. The Mathematica Series contains correspondence, memos, policy reports, project proposals, and research papers. The institutions that are often mentioned include NASA, Office of Naval Research, and Sandia Corporation. Topics, among others, relate to analysis of military conflicts, economics of the space program, management research, or peaceful use of nuclear energy. Some materials related to Mathematica Series are still scattered across the rest of the collection.
Morgenstern habitually incorporated into his files pertinent thoughts or information that might be useful for later consideration. Consequently, the Subject Files and Writings and Speeches Series often include letters, memoranda, lecture notes, writings by others, mathematics, printed material, and other Items. Thus, a file for a topic or publication in 1963 may contain relevant dated material from other years and decades.
The diaries, 1917-1977, are relatively complete, but Morgenstern did not write daily or every month. There are significant gaps: 1918-1920; Feb.-May 1938; March 1946-Jan. 1947; and Sept. 1951-Feb. 1952. Shorter gaps also occur in April-May 1924, Sept. 1925; June-July 1948; and April 1949. The diaries are in the Writings and Speeches Series.
Morgenstern's library of printed material was donated to New York University.
Addition (06-067) (2452 items, 13.5 lin. ft.; dated 1935-1976) contains primarily published works by Morgenstern and his major co-authors such as John von Neumann and Gerald L. Thompson in English, French, Spanish, Italian, and German arranged in alphabetical order. Important works contained in this series include typed manuscript portions of Theory of Games and Economic Behavior with annotations, draft chapters of the Question of National Defense, Long Term Planning with Models of Static and Dynamic Open Expanding Economies, the Mathematica Economic Analysis of the Space Shuttle System and some correspondence, as well as supporting documentation and statistics. There are also three audiotape reels with Morgenstern's lectures.
Europe -- Economic conditions; Government consultants; Business consultants; Cold War; Nuclear energy; International finance; Military policy; Prices; Depressions -- 1929; Austrian school of economics; Diaries; Economics; Economics -- Study and teaching; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; United States -- Defenses; Economists -- United States; Audiocassettes; Economic forecasting; United States -- Economic conditions; Economic history; Videocassettes; Economics -- Statistical methods; Economics, Mathematical; Tape reels; Money; Game theory; United States -- Foreign relations; Business cycles; Audiovisual materials; United States -- Military policy; Vorob'ev, N. N. (Nikolai Nikolaevich), 1925-; Universitt Wien -- Faculty; Von Neumann, John, 1903-1957; Thompson, Gerald Luther, 1923-; United States. Navy; Princeton University; Shubik, Martin; New York University; Mathematica, Inc.; Haberler, Gottfried, 1900-1995; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-; Burns, Eveline Mabel Richardson, 1900-; De Viti de Marco, Antonio, 1858-1943; Morgenstern, Oskar, 1902-1977
- Information Series, 1866-1992 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Writings, memoranda, lists, letters, and printed material concerning Morgenstern's life, career, and publications. Arranged into autobiographical, biographical, and bibliographical categories.
  - Biographical Materials (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical Materials (Box 1)
  - Bibliography, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1918-1977
  The bulk of this series consists of letters written to Morgenstern by economists, educators, businessmen, and officials of governments and organizations. Communications from personal friends and family are minimal in a collection that is primarily professional. Copies of Morgenstern's letters are available for some periods. Arranged into chronological groups often subdivided alphabetically. Noteworthy names and topics from each folder are listed below.
  - 1918-1924: A-Z, 7 folders (Box 1)
    Includes letters from von Bismarck, Deutshche Allgemeine Zeitung, Gustav Fischer, Hans Hoffman, Hans Mayer (?), Max Reichmuth, and Othomar Spann.
  - 1925-1926: A-G (Box 1)
    Includes letters from Columbia University, F.Y. Edgeworth, and Frank A. Fetter. ALS from F.Y. Edgeworth to Morgenstern on Royal Economic Society All Souls/Oxford letterhead, dated November 21, 1925, donated by Martin Shubik as part of Acc. 2018-0050.
  - 1925-1926: H-Z, 5 folders (Box 2)
    Includes letters from F.A. Hayek, The London School of Economics, Hans Mayer (in the M and S folders), Wesley C. Mitchell, Hans Neuwirth, John Nolen, The Rockefeller Foundation, Wilhelm Roeppke, P.N. Rosenstein, Urban League, and Hans Wolf.
  - 1926-1927: A-Z, 6 folders (Box 2)
    Includes letters from American Economic Review, Irving Fisher, Alvin H. Hansen, F.A. Hayek, International Banking-Students Association, Marget, Wesley C. Mitchell, Hans Neuwirth, A.F. Pribram, The Rockefeller Foundation, F.W. Taussing, Max Thornburg, and A. Young.
  - 1926-1927: Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - 1927: Carbon Copies, 2 folders (Box 3)
    Includes letters from Gottfried Haberler, F.A. Hayek, Wesley C. Mitchell, Hans Neuwirth, The Rockefeller Foundation, A.F. Pribram, F.X. Weiss, and Allyn A. Young.
  - 1928: A-Z, 7 folders (Box 3)
    Includes letters from American Economic Review, Luige Einaudi, Irving Fisher, Gottfried Haberler, Alvin Hansen, F.A. Hayek, International Banking-Students Association, F.H. Knight, A. Marget, Hans Mayer, Wesley C. Mitchell, A.F. Pribram, The Rockefeller Foundation, P.N. Rosenstein, Verlag Julius Springer Wien, and Jacob Viner.
  - 1928: Carbon Copies (Box 3)
    Includes letters from Hans Mayer, P.N. Rosenstein, Gottfried Haberler, F.A. Hayek, Luigi Einaudi, W.(?) Eucken, Irving Fisher, Arthur W. Marget, Wesley C. Mitchell, Hans Neuwirth, F. Pribram, a report to the Rockefeller Foundation, and Allyn A. Young.
  - 1929 (Box 3)
    Includes letters from F. Zahn.
  - 1930-1932: A-R, 4 folders (Box 3)
    Includes letters from American Economic Review, Encyclopedia of Social Sciences, Alvin H. Hansen, F.A. Hayek, International Banking Students Association, Emil Kauder, Frank H. Knight, Hans Mayer, A.P. Predoehl, The Rockefeller Foundation, and Ludwig von Mises (letter from The Rockefeller Foundation).
  - 1930-1932: S-Z (Box 4)
    Includes letters from J. Schumpeter and F.W. Taussig.
  - 1928-1939: A-El (Box 4)
    Includes letters from Oskar Anderson, Henry Andrews, Osamu Arii, Walter Breisky, Robert Tuite Boothby, Eve M. Burns, Attilio Cabiati, Henry Clay, Economist, Luigi Einaudi, and Howard S. Ellis.
  - 1928-1939: Ep-Ke, 15 folders (Box 5)
    Includes letters from Ernst Epstein, Alexander Gerschenkron, Gottfried Haberler, F.A. Hayek, T. Ichitani, Per Jacobsson, Ernst John, Emil Kauder, and J.M. Keynes.
  - 1928-1939: Ki-T, 19 folders (Box 6)
    Includes letters from Viktor Kienbock, Frank H. Knight, Gunnar Myrdal, Royal Institute of International Affairs, A.W. Sanders, Karl Schlesinger, Josep Schumpeter, Felix Somary, Otto Lange, Verlag Julius Springer, and Arthur Spiethoff.
  - 1928-1939: Te-Z, 19 folders (Box 7)
    Includes letters from Telegraphendirektion fur Wien, Fritz Thalmann, Frank C. Tiarks, Stefan Varga, Marchese A. de Viti de Marco, W. Vleugels, Johannes Vondrak, and David Watson.
  - 1940-1949: A-Z, 28 folders (Box 80)
    Includes letters from Friedrich A. Hayek, G. Haberler, International Statistical Institute, Karl Menger, and John von Neumann.
  - 1950-1958: A-S, 26 folders (Box 81)
    Includes letters from T.W. Anderson, French Study Group in Applied Social Sciences, George Washington University and Stanford consultantships, Gustavo Del Vecchio, Goran Nyblen, Carl R. Ohman, personal letters, Maurice H. Peston, Andreas Predohl, Stedman B. Noble, Schatzmeister, Ronald W. Shephard, and Martin Shubik.
  - 1950-1958: T-Z, 15 folders (Box 82)
    Includes letters from Gerald Thomas, A.W. Tucker, Y.K. Wong, W.G. Waffenschmidt, William M. Young, and Edward Zabel.
  - 1959-1962: A, 13 folders (Box 82)
    Includes letters from American Association for the Advancement of Science, AIR Material Command, Alderson Associates, American Economic Association, American Rocket Society, American Statistical Association, and Atomic Energy Comission.
  - 1959-1962: B-H, 31 folders (Box 83)
    Includes letters from Boron, Carnegie, George Chacko, CONVAIR, Council on Foreign Relations, Curtiss-Wright Coporation, Henry Eccles, Econometric Society, Econometrica, Ford Foundation, Fortune Magazine, William C. Foster, C. Granger, General Motors, Friedrich A. Hayek, and Michio Hatanaka.
  - 1959-1962: I-M, 23 folders (Box 84)
    Includes letters from Information and Control, International Statistical Institute, H.M. Jackson, Robert Johnson, Emil Kauder, List-Gesellschaft, Lockheed Aircraft Corporation, Morgenstern's out-of-office correspondence, Kazuo Mizutani, Karl Menger, Julius Meinl, and Edward Marcus.
  - 1959-1962: Na-Sz, 25 folders (Box 85)
    Includes letters about personal matters, as well as Andreas Predohl, letters discussing the question of national defense, Raytheon Company, book reviews, Review of International Financial Transactions and Business Cycle, Radio Corporation of America, Rand Corporation, and Random House.
  - 1959-1962: S-Z, 22 folders (Box 86)
    Includes salaries material, as well as letters from Edgar Salin, material on shelters, Donald Shephard, Martin Shubik, Stanwell Oil and Gas Ltd, A.H. Taub, Gerald Thompson, University policies and procedures, Zeitschrift Fur Nationalokonomie, Zeitschrift Fur Wahrscheinlichkeitstheorie Und Verwandte Gebiete.
  - 1960s: A-C, 11 folders (Box 86)
    Includes letters from N.S. Afriat, Karl Borch, Admiral Burke, Carnegie Corporation, congratulatory letters, and Council on Foreign Relations.
  - 1960s: D-I, 21 folders (Box 87)
    Includes letters from Department of Commerce, Ford Foundation, General Motors, Clive Granger, Julian Gumperz, Michio Hantanaka, IBM, Institute for Advanced Studies, and Institute for Future Studies.
  - 1960s: J-Z, 38 folders (Box 88)
    Includes letters from Emil Kauder, Reinhard Kamitz, Liechtenstein-McNally, reports and papers, Master Heart Foundation, Mathematica-ONR POLAIS Study, miscellaneous universities, MRCA, Navy, OM, RAND, Rockefeller Foundation, Edgar Salin, SANDIA, S. Sagoroff, Stevens and Clark Scudder,Smalley, Texas, Texas AM University, Textile Research Institute, Walter Toman, and University of Vienna.
  - Miscellaneous United States, 1970-1977 (bulk 1974-1977), A-N, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous United States, 1970-1977 (bulk 1974-1977), O-Z, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Foreign, 1966-1967 (bulk 1974-1977), A-Z, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Chronological: 1925-1945, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Chronological: 1946-1956, 27 folders (Box 89)
  - Chronological: 1959-1967, 26 folders (Box 90)
  - Chronological: 1968-1972, 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Chronological: 1973-1974, Feb., 9 folders (Box 10)
  - Chronological: 1974, March-1977, undated, 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Recommendation Letters 1949-1958, 3 folders (Box 90)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1910-1977 and undated
  Morgenstern's publications, lectures, speeches and reviews focus upon economic theory and national and international economic problems. The diaries, written in German, cover his professional career and are also the principal source for his personal life. The writings are arranged into diaries, large chronological and alphabetical groups, and a small miscellaneous group. The chronological writings are mostly printed material and photocopies. The alphabetical writings include drafts and final copies, often incomplete, and may be manuscripts, typescripts, photocopies, or printed material. The files of alphabetical writings also include supporting papers. A particular publication may have material in both the chronological and alphabetical group.
  A later addition to Writings and Speeches has been incorporated intellectually in the list below but is physically housed in Boxes 100 and 101.
  - Diaries, 1917-1977
    - Diaries, 1917, March 14-1928, Jan. 4, 14 folders (Box 12)
    - Diaries, 1928, Jan. 21-1944, Aug. 3, 11 folders (Box 13)
    - Diaries, 1944, Aug. 5-1957, Dec. 31, 9 folders (Box 14)
    - Diaries, 1958, Jan. 3-1972, July 31, 9 folders (Box 15)
    - Diaries, 1972, Aug. 5-1977, July 17, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1910-1977
    - Teichler, Margarete. Hochzeitsgedicte, 1910-1911, Wigandsthal, Silesia (Near Grlitz) (Box 16)
    - M., M.L. Die Renaissance, II. Teil, Michelangelo, 1920. Lecture Given on March 5, 12, June 1 (Box 16)
    - Appointment and Memorandum Book, 1950 (Box 16)
    - Notes on Trip to Far East and Southeast Asia, 1954 (Box 16)
    - Interviews, 1967-1973 (Box 16)
    - Notes, Personal and Professional, on a Variety of Topics, 1975-1977 (Box 16)
  - Chronological, 1923-1977
    - Chronological, 1923-1947, 8 folders (Box 17)
    - Chronological, 1948-1955, 9 folders (Box 18)
    - Chronological, 1956-1966, 9 folders (Box 19)
    - Chronological, 1967-1972, 9 folders (Box 20)
    - Chronological, 1973-1977, undated, 7 folders (Box 21)
  - Alphabetical
    - Account of Activities During First Year of Fellowship, 1926 (Box 21)
    - The Accuracy of Economic Observations, 1949 (Box 21)
    - Aggregation and Errors in Input-Output Models, undated (Box 100)
    - Almost-symmetric Solutions of Some Symmetric n-Person Games, 1961 (Box 21)
    - The Analysis of Integrated Business and Economic Systems, General Electric, 1957 (Box 21)
    - Antonio de Viti de Marco, 1966-1968 (Box 22)
    - Applied Game Theory, 1971-1972 (Box 22)
    - Ausgaben und Grenzen der Institute fr Konjunkturforschung, 1928 (Box 22)
    - Basel Lecture, undated (Box 100)
    - Die Bedingungen der wirtschaftlichen Lebensfhigkeit sterreichs, 1938 (Box 22)
    - Bemerkungen zu Cassels Preistheorie, 1925-1926 (Box 22)
    - Cardano, the Gambling Scholar, 1953 (Box 22)
    - Chicago Lecture, 1963 (Box 100)
    - The Choice of a Transportation System, 1969 (Box 22)
    - The Cold War Is Cold Poker, 1961 (Box 22)
    - The Collaboration between Oskar Morgenstern and John von Neumann on the Theory of Games, 1976, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Collected Papers: Preface, 1974 (Box 22)
    - Columbia University Lecture at Grad Club,1966 (Box 100)
    - Command and Control Problems in the Military, 1972 (Box 22)
    - Comments on Some Defense Problems, 1965 (Box 22)
    - Competition and Collusion in Bilateral Markets, 1976, by Morgenstern and Gerhard Schwdiaur (Box 22)
    - Compositions and Exercises from School, 1918-1920 (Box 22)
    - Compositions and Exercises from School, 1919-1921, undated, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - The Compressibility of Economic Systems and the Problem of Economic Constants, 1966: 1954-1966 (Box 23)
    - Computation of Economic Programs, 1950: 1950-1951 (Box 23)
    - Critical Points in Contemporary Economic Theory, 1972: 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Defense Bonds Article, 1942 (Box 23)
    - Demand Theory, Old Manuscript, 1940 (Box 23)
    - Demand Theory Reconsidered, 1948: 1941-1971 (Box 24)
    - Descriptive, Predictive, and Normative Theory, 1972: 1971-1972 (Box 24)
    - Deterrence Paper for Killian Group, 1959 (Box 24)
    - Deterrence Strategy and Annihilation, 1960-1971, undated (Articles and Notes) (Box 24)
    - Die Bedingungen De Writschaftlichen Lebensfahigkeit Oesterreichs, 1938 (Box 100)
    - Die drei Grundtypen der Theorie des subjektiven Wertes, 1931: 1929-1931 (Box 24)
    - An Economic Program for Germany, 1947 (Box 24)
    - Economic Program for Germany, 1947 (Box 100)
    - Economic Strategies: Military Alliances and Mutual Security, 1962-1963 (Box 100)
    - Economic Systems and Philosophy, undated (Box 100)
    - Economic Theory Chapter XIV, undated (Box 100)
    - Economic Troubles Article, New York Times, 1974 (Box 24)
    - Economics and the Theory of Games, 1948 (Box 24)
    - L'conomie est-elle une science exact?, 1971: 1971-1972 (Box 24)
    - An Economist in Europe, 1952 (Box 24)
    - Economic and Social Interpretation of Events, undated (Box 100)
    - Elements (Utility-Price)" (Folder Label) (Box 24)
    - Empirical Analysis of Business Cycle, undated (Box 100)
    - Entstehung und Abbau der esterreichischen Devisenbewirtschaftung, 1937 (Box 24)
    - Entwicklungstendenzen im Federal Reserve System, 1930 (Box 25)
    - Evolution of Modern Demand Theory: A Collection of Essays, 1972: Notes for Preface, 1971 (Box 25)
    - Expanding and Contracting Economies, 1976: 1975-1976 (Box 25)